<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="somersetballet.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="somersetballet.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-14T01:56:57+00:00</updated><id>somersetballet.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Somerset School of Ballet</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Foot Positions</title><link href="somersetballet.com/blog/2024/class1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Foot Positions"/><published>2024-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>somersetballet.com/blog/2024/class1</id><content type="html" xml:base="somersetballet.com/blog/2024/class1/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/FootPositions-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/FootPositions-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/FootPositions-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/FootPositions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="ballet-positions-of-the-feet">Ballet Positions of the Feet</h3> <p>These positions form the foundation of ballet technique and are essential for proper alignment, balance, and movement.</p> <p>Here are some of my notes, as an instructor:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>First Position</strong></p> <ul> <li>Heels together with toes turned out, forming a straight line.</li> <li>Legs are rotated outward from the hips.</li> <li>Lift your arches</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Second Position</strong></p> <ul> <li>Feet are turned out and placed about hip-width apart.</li> <li>Heels remain on the same line as in first position.</li> <li>Lift your arches</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Third Position</strong></p> <ul> <li>One foot is placed in front of the other, with the heel of the front foot touching the arch of the back foot.</li> <li>Both feet are turned outwards.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Fourth Position</strong></p> <ul> <li>One foot is placed in front of the other, about one foot’s length apart.</li> <li>Both feet are turned outwards, with the heel of the front foot aligned with the toes of the back foot.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Fifth Position</strong></p> <ul> <li>One foot is placed in front of the other, with the heel of the front foot touching the toes of the back foot.</li> <li>Both feet are turned outwards, forming two parallel lines.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Sixth Position (Parallel)</strong></p> <ul> <li>Feet are parallel to each other, typically about hip-width apart.</li> <li>Toes are pointing forward, not turned out.</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <p>To check your <em>natural</em> turnout, bend your knees in any position and make sure your knee aligns with your toe. If your knee is inside, turn your foot inward. If your knee is outside, turn your foot outward.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="class,"/><category term="technique,"/><category term="notes,"/><category term="positions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'll walk you through the first 5 positions of the feet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What to wear for your first class?</title><link href="somersetballet.com/blog/2024/uniform/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to wear for your first class?"/><published>2024-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>somersetballet.com/blog/2024/uniform</id><content type="html" xml:base="somersetballet.com/blog/2024/uniform/"><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to ballet, one thing you’ll do a lot is stare at yourself in the mirror. So, first and foremost, wear whatever makes you feel confident and comfortable. When attending our drop-in classes, feel free to wear comfortable gym attire and go barefoot.</p> <p>If you’re looking to build a classic ballet wardrobe, I recommend checking out <a href="https://www.discountdance.com/dancewear/">Discount Dance</a> for reliable, well-priced options.</p> <h3 id="leotard">Leotard</h3> <p>The leotard, often called a “bodysuit,” should fit snugly. Personally, I prefer classic designs without lace, as they tend to wear out quickly. Brands like Bloch, Capezio, and So Danca are my go-tos.</p> <p>Here’s one of my favorites: <a href="https://www.sodanca.com/collections/women-dancewear-leotards/products/annie-d379?variant=44510104256674">Classic Black with A Fun Back from So Danca</a></p> <h3 id="tights">Tights</h3> <p>Convertible tights are my preference—they have a hole at the foot which can be rolled up for barefoot dancing or worn with street shoes outside of class. I opt for soft fabric over stiff mesh, as it’s more comfortable, though likely to tear.</p> <p>Here’s what I wear: <a href="https://www.capezio.com/ultra-soft-transition-tight-with-back-seam">Capezio Ultra Soft Transition Tight with Back Seam in Light Pink</a></p> <h3 id="shoes">Shoes</h3> <p>Ballet shoes are typically made from leather or canvas. Many experienced dancers, including myself, prefer canvas split-soled shoes for their flexibility.</p> <p>Here’s my choice: <a href="https://www.capezio.com/hanami-ballet-shoe">Capezio Canvas Ballet Shoe</a></p> <h3 id="pointe-shoes">Pointe Shoes</h3> <p>Pointe shoes are highly individualized and require a professional fitting. Dancers typically begin wearing pointe shoes around age 10 after auditioning and being fitted by a specialist.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="uniform"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some tips on dressing for your first ballet class]]></summary></entry></feed>