<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://somersetballet.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://somersetballet.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-19T21:28:26+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Somerset School of Ballet</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Honoring MLK Day: Celebrating Black Ballerinas in Ballet History</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2025/mlk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Honoring MLK Day: Celebrating Black Ballerinas in Ballet History"/><published>2025-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2025/mlk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2025/mlk/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="honoring-martin-luther-king-jr-day-celebrating-black-ballerinas-who-shaped-ballet-history">Honoring Martin Luther King Jr. Day: Celebrating Black Ballerinas Who Shaped Ballet History</h1> <p>As we reflect on the legacy of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and his dedication to equality and justice, it’s a meaningful time to celebrate the achievements of Black artists who have broken barriers and made history. In the world of ballet, numerous Black ballerinas have inspired generations through their grace, resilience, and artistry.</p> <p>Here are just a few of the incredible dancers who have left an indelible mark on ballet history:</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/misty.jpg" alt="Misty Copeland"/></p> <h2 id="misty-copeland"><strong>Misty Copeland</strong></h2> <p>A true trailblazer, Misty Copeland became the first African American female principal dancer with the prestigious American Ballet Theatre in 2015. Known for her strength, artistry, and advocacy, Misty has paved the way for countless dancers and remains a symbol of perseverance and excellence.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/raven.jpg" alt="Raven Wilkinson"/></p> <h2 id="raven-wilkinson"><strong>Raven Wilkinson</strong></h2> <p>Raven Wilkinson was one of the first Black ballerinas to perform with a major ballet company, joining the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo in 1955. Her courage in facing discrimination and her dedication to her craft continue to inspire dancers worldwide.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/lauren.jpg" alt="Lauren Anderson"/></p> <h2 id="lauren-anderson"><strong>Lauren Anderson</strong></h2> <p>A groundbreaking performer, Lauren Anderson became one of the first Black principal dancers of a major ballet company when she earned the title at Houston Ballet in 1990. She’s also an advocate for arts education, inspiring young dancers to dream big.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/alicia_graf_mack.jpg" alt="Alicia Graf Mack"/></p> <h2 id="alicia-graf-mack"><strong>Alicia Graf Mack</strong></h2> <p>A celebrated performer and now the dean and director of Juilliard’s dance division, Alicia Graf Mack has had a remarkable career blending ballet and modern dance. Her contributions to dance education ensure the next generation of artists continues to thrive.</p> <p><em>Fun fact: I grew up with and trained under the incredible Graf sisters at Ballet Royale. Their influence and guidance played a huge role in shaping my journey as a dancer.</em></p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/marion-cuyjet.jpg" alt="Marion Cuyjet"/></p> <h2 id="marion-cuyjet"><strong>Marion Cuyjet</strong></h2> <p>Known as the “Mother of Black Dance in Philadelphia,” Marion Cuyjet established dance schools that trained many prominent Black dancers during the mid-20th century. Her commitment to fostering talent changed the trajectory of countless careers.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/Virginia_Johnson_1983.jpeg" alt="Virginia Johnson"/></p> <h2 id="virginia-johnson"><strong>Virginia Johnson</strong></h2> <p>As a founding member and principal dancer of Dance Theatre of Harlem, Virginia Johnson’s influence spans both the stage and beyond. She has since become a celebrated artistic director, shaping the future of the company and continuing its mission of inclusion.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/mlk/michaela.jpg" alt="Michaela DePrince"/></p> <h2 id="a-tribute-to-michaela-deprince">A Tribute to Michaela DePrince</h2> <p>This year, we mourn the heartbreaking loss of Michaela DePrince, who passed away at just 29 years old. Michaela inspired countless artists with her remarkable journey from adversity to the global stage. As a principal dancer with the Dutch National Ballet, her talent, resilience, and advocacy for diversity in ballet left an indelible mark. Her legacy reminds us of the ongoing importance of inclusion and representation in the arts.</p> <h3 id="continuing-the-legacy">Continuing the Legacy</h3> <p>At Somerset School of Ballet, we are committed to honoring these incredible pioneers by fostering an inclusive environment where every dancer can thrive. Their stories remind us of the power of perseverance and the beauty of diversity in ballet.</p> <p>Take a moment today to reflect on these inspiring figures and the path they’ve paved for future generations.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="MLKDay"/><category term="BlackBallerinas"/><category term="BalletHistory"/><category term="Representation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflect on the achievements of groundbreaking Black ballerinas who shaped ballet history and inspired generations, as we honor Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s legacy of equality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Office Hours</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2025/office-hours/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Office Hours"/><published>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2025/office-hours</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2025/office-hours/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-to-make-the-most-of-office-hours-at-the-studio">How to Make the Most of Office Hours at the Studio</h1> <p>As we gear up for the performance, I’m excited to offer <strong>Office Hours</strong> as a flexible way for dancers to get one-on-one or small-group rehearsal time without needing a full private session. Whether you’re using this time to clean up choreography, work on entrances, or ask clarifying questions, here’s a guide to help you understand how to sign up, what to expect, and how to come prepared so you make the most of your session.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-are-office-hours">What Are Office Hours?</h2> <p>Office Hours are short, bookable rehearsal slots where dancers can get personalized help during a set block of time. This is perfect for:</p> <ul> <li>Fine-tuning a tricky section of your piece.</li> <li>Getting feedback on a solo or duet.</li> <li>Clarifying stage directions, timing, or transitions.<br/> Think of it like an “open tutoring session” for your ballet!</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="how-to-sign-up-for-office-hours">How to Sign Up for Office Hours:</h2> <ol> <li><strong>Check the Weekly Schedule:</strong> Office Hours are held on <strong>Wednesdays from 5:30 pm to 6:30 pm</strong>.</li> <li><strong>Reserve Your Spot:</strong> Send me a message to reserve a <strong>15-minute slot</strong>. You can request a longer slot if available, but shorter sessions help me give everyone time.</li> <li><strong>Confirmation:</strong> Once I confirm your slot, it’s yours! If you’re unable to make it, please let me know as soon as possible so I can offer the spot to another dancer.</li> </ol> <hr/> <h2 id="what-to-expect-when-you-arrive">What to Expect When You Arrive:</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Shared Space:</strong> Sometimes, you may share the studio with another dancer who’s rehearsing nearby or waiting for their slot. Be mindful of your time and noise level so everyone gets the focus they need.</li> <li><strong>Be a Supportive Audience:</strong> When you’re not warming up or reviewing for your timeslot, it’s customary to sit up front under the mirrors and act as a supportive audience for your peers. Encourage and cheer them on—it makes a big difference!</li> <li><strong>Short and Focused:</strong> 15-minute slots fly by! This isn’t a full private rehearsal but rather a concentrated time to address one or two key points.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="how-to-come-prepared">How to Come Prepared:</h2> <p>To make the most of your time, come with a clear <strong>intention</strong> for your session. Here are a few examples of what a productive session might focus on:</p> <ul> <li>“I need help smoothing out my arm transitions in the final combination.”</li> <li>“Can we review my stage entrance for counts 5–8?”</li> <li>“I want to make sure my pirouette sequence is clean and controlled.”</li> </ul> <p>This gives me a clear idea of where to direct our time so we can dive right in and get as much done as possible.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="tips-for-making-the-most-of-office-hours">Tips for Making the Most of Office Hours:</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Warm Up Beforehand:</strong> Come stretched and warmed up so you’re ready to go as soon as your slot begins.</li> <li><strong>Bring Notes:</strong> If you’ve written down any questions or corrections, bring them so we can reference them easily.</li> <li><strong>Be Open to Feedback:</strong> Sometimes fixing one section will reveal new areas to focus on. Use the feedback you get to apply corrections across the rest of your choreography.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="why-office-hours-are-here-for-you">Why Office Hours Are Here for You:</h2> <p>These rehearsal slots are designed to support you as you prepare for the show, without requiring a big time or financial commitment. Whether you’re polishing small details or building confidence in your piece, Office Hours are here to help you feel your best on performance day.</p> <p>If you’re ready to reserve your slot, send me a message, and let’s get to work!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this post, learn about Somerset School of Ballet's new office hours—designed to give dancers personalized support during Debut rehearsals, with opportunities to refine technique, ask questions, and get quick feedback.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tips for Aspiring Young Dancers</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/tips-for-young-dancers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips for Aspiring Young Dancers"/><published>2024-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/tips-for-young-dancers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/tips-for-young-dancers/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="tips-for-aspiring-young-dancers">Tips for Aspiring Young Dancers</h1> <p>Starting a journey in ballet is exciting, inspiring, and sometimes a little overwhelming. For young dancers, finding the right balance between discipline and joy is key to nurturing a lifelong love for the art. Here are some practical tips to help your budding dancer thrive:</p> <h2 id="1-focus-on-the-fundamentals"><strong>1. Focus on the Fundamentals</strong></h2> <p>Ballet is built on a strong foundation of technique. Encourage your dancer to focus on proper alignment, posture, and basic positions. Mastering the basics will make advanced movements easier and more graceful over time.</p> <h2 id="2-celebrate-progress-not-perfection"><strong>2. Celebrate Progress, Not Perfection</strong></h2> <p>Ballet can be demanding, but it’s important to celebrate small victories. Whether it’s holding a balance longer or nailing a new step, every bit of progress is worth recognizing.</p> <h2 id="3-foster-creativity"><strong>3. Foster Creativity</strong></h2> <p>Encourage your dancer to explore their creativity by improvising to music or making up short dances at home. This builds confidence and a deeper connection to the art form.</p> <h2 id="4-prioritize-consistency"><strong>4. Prioritize Consistency</strong></h2> <p>Regular practice is key to improvement. Set a schedule that includes class attendance and short at-home practice sessions to reinforce what they learn.</p> <h2 id="5-encourage-a-healthy-mindset"><strong>5. Encourage a Healthy Mindset</strong></h2> <p>Help your dancer approach challenges with positivity. Remind them that mistakes are part of the learning process and that every professional dancer started where they are now.</p> <h2 id="6-build-strength-and-flexibility"><strong>6. Build Strength and Flexibility</strong></h2> <p>Introduce exercises like gentle stretching, core strengthening, or balance work to support their training. Physical fitness complements ballet technique and prevents injuries.</p> <h2 id="7-support-their-goals"><strong>7. Support Their Goals</strong></h2> <p>Listen to your dancer’s aspirations, whether they dream of performing in <em>The Nutcracker</em> or simply enjoy dancing for fun. Tailor your support to their individual goals.</p> <h2 id="8-make-it-fun"><strong>8. Make It Fun!</strong></h2> <p>Keep the joy alive by incorporating fun elements, like themed dance days, new music, or creative costumes for home practice. Ballet should always feel like a celebration of movement.</p> <h2 id="9-encourage-artistic-exploration"><strong>9. Encourage Artistic Exploration</strong></h2> <p>Expose your dancer to performances, documentaries, and books about ballet. Seeing professionals in action can ignite their passion and provide inspiration.</p> <h2 id="10-partner-with-their-teacher"><strong>10. Partner with Their Teacher</strong></h2> <p>Communication with your dancer’s teacher is invaluable. Share their goals, progress, and any challenges to create a supportive environment for growth.</p> <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3> <p>Every dancer’s journey is unique. By focusing on technique, fostering creativity, and keeping the joy alive, you can help your young dancer build confidence, embrace challenges, and fall in love with ballet—one plié at a time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="YoungDancers"/><category term="BalletTips"/><category term="Inspiration"/><category term="Growth"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Help your young dancer thrive with these practical tips for building confidence, fostering creativity, and embracing the joy of ballet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Representation in Ballet: Why It Matters</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/representation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Representation in Ballet: Why It Matters"/><published>2024-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/representation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/representation/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="representation-in-ballet-why-it-matters">Representation in Ballet: Why It Matters</h1> <p>Ballet is an art form rooted in centuries of tradition, beauty, and discipline. However, for much of its history, ballet has not always reflected the diversity of the world around it. As we continue to move toward a more inclusive and equitable future, representation in ballet has become not only a goal but a necessity. Here’s why it matters:</p> <h2 id="expanding-the-narrative"><strong>Expanding the Narrative</strong></h2> <p>Every dancer brings their unique story, background, and perspective to the stage. By embracing diversity, ballet can expand its narrative and reflect the wide range of experiences and cultures that make up our global community. When audiences see themselves represented on stage, the art becomes more accessible and relatable.</p> <h2 id="inspiring-the-next-generation"><strong>Inspiring the Next Generation</strong></h2> <p>Representation matters most to those who dream. When young dancers see performers who look like them, they’re more likely to believe that they, too, can achieve their goals. Misty Copeland’s rise to principal dancer at the American Ballet Theatre inspired countless dancers of color to pursue their dreams despite historical barriers.</p> <h2 id="challenging-traditional-norms"><strong>Challenging Traditional Norms</strong></h2> <p>For many years, ballet adhered to rigid aesthetic standards that excluded dancers based on their body type, skin color, or cultural background. Today, companies like Dance Theatre of Harlem and others are redefining what it means to be a ballerina by celebrating individuality and breaking outdated norms.</p> <h2 id="fostering-creativity-and-growth"><strong>Fostering Creativity and Growth</strong></h2> <p>Diversity fosters creativity. When dancers from different backgrounds collaborate, they bring fresh ideas, styles, and techniques to the art form. This blending of influences not only enriches performances but also pushes the boundaries of what ballet can be.</p> <h2 id="creating-a-welcoming-community"><strong>Creating a Welcoming Community</strong></h2> <p>An inclusive ballet world is a welcoming one. Representation sends a powerful message that ballet is for everyone—regardless of race, gender, socioeconomic status, or ability. By opening its doors, the ballet community ensures its longevity and relevance in a changing world.</p> <h3 id="steps-toward-change">Steps Toward Change</h3> <p>While progress has been made, there’s still work to be done. Here are some ways the ballet community can continue to foster representation:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Diversify leadership</strong>: Representation starts at the top. Companies, schools, and organizations should prioritize hiring diverse leaders and educators.</li> <li><strong>Eliminate financial barriers</strong>: Ballet training can be expensive. Scholarships and outreach programs can help make it more accessible to underrepresented communities.</li> <li><strong>Update repertoire and storytelling</strong>: Introducing new ballets that reflect diverse stories and experiences allows the art to evolve and connect with modern audiences.</li> <li><strong>Provide support systems</strong>: Mentorship programs and inclusive policies can ensure dancers feel supported and valued throughout their careers.</li> </ul> <p>At Somerset School of Ballet, we believe that every dancer deserves the chance to shine. By fostering an inclusive environment and celebrating diversity, we hope to inspire a new generation of dancers who will carry ballet into a brighter, more inclusive future.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="Representation"/><category term="DiversityInBallet"/><category term="BalletInclusion"/><category term="BalletHistory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover why representation in ballet matters for expanding narratives, inspiring young dancers, fostering creativity, and building a more inclusive community.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Difference Between a Preparation for Pointe Class and a Regular Ballet Class</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/prep-for-point/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Difference Between a Preparation for Pointe Class and a Regular Ballet Class"/><published>2024-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/prep-for-point</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/prep-for-point/"><![CDATA[<p>As students progress in their ballet journey, many dream of dancing en pointe. However, before taking that step, it’s essential to understand the difference between a regular ballet class and a preparation for pointe class. Pointe work demands a unique level of strength and technique, and the preparation class is a crucial step toward safely achieving that goal.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="regular-ballet-class-building-foundations"><strong>Regular Ballet Class: Building Foundations</strong></h3> <p>In a regular ballet class, dancers focus on developing the foundations of ballet technique. Through barre, center practice, and across-the-floor exercises, dancers improve:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Coordination and musicality</strong></li> <li><strong>Strength and flexibility</strong></li> <li><strong>Ballet vocabulary and technique</strong></li> </ul> <p>These classes focus on core movements like pliés, tendus, jumps, and turns, aiming to create a well-rounded dancer. However, they do not specifically target the muscle groups needed for pointe work, making a separate preparation class essential for dancers aiming to go en pointe.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="preparation-for-pointe-class-strength-for-pointe-work"><strong>Preparation for Pointe Class: Strength for Pointe Work</strong></h3> <p>A preparation for pointe class is different from a regular ballet class because it is specifically designed to build the necessary strength, balance, and alignment needed for pointe work. In my pointe prep class, we focus on:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Foot and Ankle Strength</strong>: Through theraband exercises, relevés, and foot articulation drills, we develop the strength needed to support the body en pointe.</li> <li><strong>Core Stability and Balance</strong>: Exercises like planks, single-leg relevés, and balance drills improve core strength and stability, crucial for maintaining balance en pointe.</li> <li><strong>Alignment and Turnout</strong>: We focus on proper turnout and body alignment to ensure safety and prevent injuries, with exercises that strengthen the hips, legs, and feet.</li> <li><strong>Flexibility</strong>: Flexibility in the feet and Achilles tendons is important for smooth transitions onto pointe. In class, we perform focused stretches to improve range of motion.</li> </ul> <p>Unlike regular ballet classes, the preparation for pointe class minimizes complex choreography and jumping, instead focusing on building the strength and control needed for pointe work.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="why-age-matters"><strong>Why Age Matters</strong></h3> <p>No student should begin pointe work before they are physically ready. I require students to be at least <strong>13 years old</strong> before going en pointe, and no dancer under <strong>11 years old</strong> should take a pointe prep class. This ensures that the bones and muscles have developed enough to safely handle the demands of pointe. The preparation class gives students the time they need to build strength, flexibility, and alignment, ensuring they are ready for the challenges of pointe work when the time comes.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="complementary-to-regular-ballet-classes"><strong>Complementary to Regular Ballet Classes</strong></h3> <p>A preparation for pointe class works in tandem with regular ballet classes. The regular class helps dancers develop broad ballet technique, while the pointe prep class builds the specific strength and control needed for pointe. Together, they provide a comprehensive ballet education, preparing dancers to reach their goals safely and confidently.</p> <hr/> <p>By focusing on specific exercises designed to strengthen the body for pointe work, my preparation for pointe class will ensure that when the time comes, students are ready to take their next step in ballet—en pointe.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="ballet,"/><category term="point"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A preparation for pointe class designed to build strength, balance, and flexibility, ensuring dancers are ready for the demands of pointe work.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ballet vs. Barre: Choosing the Right Class for Your Goals</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/barre-v-ballet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ballet vs. Barre: Choosing the Right Class for Your Goals"/><published>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/barre-v-ballet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/barre-v-ballet/"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve ever searched for a dance-inspired workout or are looking to explore the world of ballet, you’ve likely come across both ballet and barre classes. While they share some similarities, these two types of classes offer distinct experiences. Whether you’re working toward fitness goals or honing your dance technique, understanding the differences between barre and ballet will help you make the right choice for your needs.</p> <h3 id="what-is-a-barre-class"><strong>What is a Barre Class?</strong></h3> <p>Barre classes take inspiration from ballet movements and techniques but combine them with elements of Pilates, yoga, and strength training. These classes use the ballet barre as a tool to help improve balance, flexibility, and strength. The focus is often on small, controlled movements and repetitions designed to tone major muscle groups—particularly in the legs, core, and glutes—similar to a standard fitness class.</p> <p>Barre is a great choice if you’re looking for a low-impact, full-body workout that focuses on sculpting muscles without the need for extensive choreography or prior dance experience. It’s accessible to all fitness levels and offers a welcoming environment for anyone seeking to improve their fitness in a graceful way.</p> <h3 id="what-is-a-ballet-class"><strong>What is a Ballet Class?</strong></h3> <p>A ballet class, on the other hand, centers on classical dance training. It emphasizes technique, posture, coordination, and flexibility while also fostering artistic expression. Students learn traditional positions and movements like pliés, tendus, and pirouettes, developing a strong foundation in dance that can be built upon over time.</p> <p>One key difference is that ballet focuses on activating and strengthening smaller, often overlooked muscle groups—like those in your feet, ankles, and neck—that are not typically targeted in other fitness routines. These minor muscles help support balance, precision, and the fluidity of movement unique to ballet.</p> <p>Ballet classes are ideal if you’re interested in learning the art of dance, developing long-term technique, or even preparing for performances. While ballet certainly strengthens and tones the body, its primary focus is on learning dance vocabulary and improving skills over time. Ballet is often progressive, meaning that students advance in levels as they master specific techniques.</p> <h3 id="which-should-you-choose"><strong>Which Should You Choose?</strong></h3> <p>The choice between a barre class and a ballet class depends on your personal goals:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Choose a Barre Class if:</strong></p> <ul> <li>You’re seeking a fitness-focused workout.</li> <li>You want to tone and strengthen major muscle groups like legs, glutes, and core.</li> <li>You’re looking for low-impact exercise that incorporates elements of dance.</li> <li>You’re new to fitness and want a welcoming, non-intimidating environment.</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p><strong>Choose a Ballet Class if:</strong></p> <ul> <li>You’re passionate about learning dance technique.</li> <li>You want to develop posture, balance, and grace by working both major and minor muscle groups.</li> <li>You’re interested in progressing through levels of ballet or even performing.</li> <li>You’re looking for both mental and physical challenges, as ballet combines artistry with technique.</li> <li>Six-year-old you always wanted to take a ballet class, but your parents signed you up for soccer instead 😉</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="complementary-practices"><strong>Complementary Practices</strong></h3> <p>It’s worth noting that ballet and barre don’t have to be mutually exclusive. Many dancers use barre classes as a form of cross-training to strengthen muscles that support their dance practice. Likewise, those who fall in love with the grace and precision of barre might find themselves inspired to dive deeper into the art of ballet.</p> <p>Both barre and ballet have incredible benefits, and the best part is that you can enjoy either (or both!) depending on where you are in your fitness or dance journey.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="ballet,"/><category term="barre,"/><category term="fitness,"/><category term="dance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn the key differences between barre and ballet classes, and when each is the right choice for your fitness or dance journey.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why We Cap Class Sizes at Somerset School of Ballet</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/class-size/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why We Cap Class Sizes at Somerset School of Ballet"/><published>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/class-size</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/class-size/"><![CDATA[<p>Ballet is unique in the way it fosters both individual and collective growth in class. One of the most valuable aspects of ballet is that, regardless of class size, a skilled instructor will provide 1-on-1 corrections that benefit everyone. In ballet, even when a correction is made to one dancer, it’s really a lesson for all to absorb and apply. A good correction helps not just the individual, but the entire class move toward better technique and artistry.</p> <p>At Somerset School of Ballet, we take this personal approach a step further. We intentionally cap our class sizes to ensure that each student receives even more focused, semi-private attention. By keeping classes small, our instructors have the opportunity to interact with every student, helping them refine their movements, adjust posture, or improve technique in a way that is tailored to their needs.</p> <h3 id="what-does-a-small-class-size-mean-for-you"><strong>What Does a Small Class Size Mean for You?</strong></h3> <p>In a smaller class, students benefit from more personalized feedback and hands-on instruction. Here’s what that looks like at Somerset School of Ballet:</p> <ul> <li><strong>More Time for Individual Attention:</strong> Every dancer gets the chance to be seen, understood, and guided by their instructor in a more intimate setting.</li> <li><strong>Faster Progress:</strong> When a teacher has more time to address each student’s strengths and areas for improvement, dancers can work on corrections faster and more effectively.</li> <li><strong>Supportive Learning Environment:</strong> With fewer students, the classroom environment becomes more comfortable for asking questions and receiving corrections. Everyone benefits from the instructor’s close observation.</li> <li><strong>Enhanced Confidence:</strong> Knowing that you’ll have dedicated time with your teacher helps build confidence, ensuring you’re developing not just as a dancer, but as an individual.</li> </ul> <h3 id="semi-private-lessons-in-every-class"><strong>Semi-Private Lessons in Every Class</strong></h3> <p>At Somerset School of Ballet, we treat every class like a semi-private lesson. Our goal is to create a space where every dancer feels seen, valued, and supported in their personal ballet journey. Whether it’s your first time at the barre or you’re preparing for a performance, you’ll receive guidance that’s tailored to help you achieve your personal best.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="class-size,"/><category term="learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how Somerset School of Ballet provides personalized instruction by capping class sizes for a semi-private experience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Transparency in Dance: Understanding the True Cost of a Ballet Performance</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/performance-costs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transparency in Dance: Understanding the True Cost of a Ballet Performance"/><published>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/performance-costs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/performance-costs/"><![CDATA[<p>When enrolling your child in dance, it’s easy to get swept up in the excitement of recitals and performances. However, many families are surprised by the hidden costs that can quickly add up—costs that aren’t always made clear up front. From hair and makeup to costumes and accessories, dance performances can be an expensive undertaking.</p> <p>At our studio, we believe in full transparency and in being good stewards of your money. We understand that dance is an investment, and we want to make sure you know exactly what you’re signing up for. By providing clear information about potential costs, we aim to help families plan ahead without unexpected surprises.</p> <p>Below, we’ve compiled a list of potential expenses related to our upcoming <strong>“Debut”</strong> performance, including hair and makeup supplies, dance attire, and costume costs. By breaking down these expenses, we hope to make the financial commitment clear and manageable. Here’s what you can expect:</p> <h3 id="basic-performance-materials"><strong>Basic Performance Materials:</strong></h3> <p>These are common items that most dancers will need for the performance. If you already own some of these items, great! If not, here’s what you can expect to pay:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Hairnet:</strong> $1 - $5 (for a pack)</li> <li><strong>Bobby Pins:</strong> $2 - $5 (for a pack of 50-100)</li> <li><strong>Hair Ties:</strong> $3 - $8 (for a pack of 10-50)</li> <li><strong>Hair Spray:</strong> $4 - $15 (for a can)</li> <li><strong>Foundation:</strong> $8 - $40 (depending on brand and coverage)</li> <li><strong>Blush:</strong> $5 - $30 (depending on brand and type)</li> <li><strong>Lipstick:</strong> $5 - $30 (depending on brand and type)</li> <li><strong>Mascara:</strong> $7 - $25 (depending on brand and formula)</li> <li><strong>Eyeliner:</strong> $5 - $20 (depending on brand and type)</li> <li><strong>Eye Shadow:</strong> $5 - $40 (depending on brand and palette size)</li> <li><strong>Pink Ballet Shoes:</strong> $20 - $35</li> <li><strong>Pink Tights:</strong> $8 - $16</li> </ul> <p><strong>Total Estimated Cost for Basic Performance Materials:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Lower End:</strong> $73</li> <li><strong>Higher End:</strong> $259</li> </ul> <h3 id="class-demonstration-materials"><strong>Class Demonstration Materials:</strong></h3> <p>For those participating in the class demonstration, here’s what you may need:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Black Leotard:</strong> $15 - $25</li> <li><strong>Black Ballet Skirt:</strong> $10 - $30</li> </ul> <p><strong>Estimated Cost for Class Demonstration:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Lower End:</strong> $25</li> <li><strong>Higher End:</strong> $55</li> </ul> <h3 id="class-ensemble-costume"><strong>Class Ensemble Costume:</strong></h3> <p>For group performances or ensemble pieces, the expected cost of the costume is:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Beginner Dance Costume:</strong> $20 - $40</li> </ul> <h3 id="solo-performance-costume"><strong>Solo Performance Costume:</strong></h3> <p>For those dancers performing a solo, an additional costume may be required:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Solo Costume:</strong> $30 - $50</li> </ul> <h3 id="total-estimated-costs"><strong>Total Estimated Costs:</strong></h3> <p><strong>Class Demonstration Only:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Lower End:</strong> $25 (Demo) + $73 (Basic Materials) = $98</li> <li><strong>Higher End:</strong> $55 (Demo) + $259 (Basic Materials) = $314</li> </ul> <p><strong>Class Demonstration + Class Ensemble:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Lower End:</strong> $45 (Demo + Ensemble) + $73 (Basic Materials) = $118</li> <li><strong>Higher End:</strong> $95 (Demo + Ensemble) + $259 (Basic Materials) = $354</li> </ul> <p><strong>Class Demonstration + Class Ensemble + Solo Piece:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Lower End:</strong> $75 (Demo + Ensemble + Solo) + $73 (Basic Materials) = $148</li> <li><strong>Higher End:</strong> $145 (Demo + Ensemble + Solo) + $259 (Basic Materials) = $404</li> </ul> <h3 id="final-thoughts"><strong>Final Thoughts</strong></h3> <p>We understand that participating in a dance performance is a significant financial commitment. Our goal is to ensure that every family knows what to expect from the very beginning. We’re dedicated to making this experience not only magical for the dancers but also transparent and manageable for our families. If you have any questions about these costs, feel free to reach out!</p> <p>Thank you for supporting your dancer and being part of this exciting journey!</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="performance"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get the full breakdown of potential performance costs and how we ensure transparency for our families in our upcoming 'Debut' ballet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mastering the Basics: Understanding the Positions of the Arms in Ballet</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/arms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mastering the Basics: Understanding the Positions of the Arms in Ballet"/><published>2024-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/arms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/arms/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ArmPositions-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ArmPositions-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ArmPositions-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/ArmPositions.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Ballet is a dance form that beautifully combines grace, strength, and precision. While much emphasis is often placed on the positions of the feet, the positions of the arms are equally vital in creating the elegant lines that ballet is known for. For beginners, mastering these basic arm positions is a fundamental step toward developing a strong ballet foundation. Let’s explore the five primary positions of the arms in ballet and how they contribute to your technique and artistry.</p> <h3 id="1-first-position-première-position"><strong>1. First Position (Première Position)</strong></h3> <p>In the first position, the arms form a soft, rounded shape in front of the body, just above the waist. Imagine holding a beach ball lightly with your fingertips almost touching. Your shoulders should remain down and relaxed, and your elbows lifted to create a gentle curve. This position helps dancers build awareness of their arm placement and core engagement.</p> <h3 id="2-second-position-seconde-position"><strong>2. Second Position (Seconde Position)</strong></h3> <p>From first position, the arms open outward to the sides, maintaining a gentle curve. The palms face forward, and the elbows remain slightly bent to avoid hyperextension. In second position, dancers learn to expand their reach while maintaining a graceful line, which is essential for balance and poise in dance.</p> <h3 id="3-third-position-troisième-position"><strong>3. Third Position (Troisième Position)</strong></h3> <p>In third position, one arm remains in first position in front of the body, while the other arm extends to second position. This position is less commonly used in modern ballet but is a great exercise for beginners to practice coordination and control. It prepares dancers for more complex arm movements and transitions.</p> <h3 id="4-fourth-position-quatrième-position"><strong>4. Fourth Position (Quatrième Position)</strong></h3> <p>Fourth position involves one arm in a high position above the head and the other in first position in front of the body. The arm above the head should be slightly curved, with the palm facing downward, and the shoulders remain relaxed. This position requires strong core support and helps dancers practice the alignment and balance necessary for more advanced movements.</p> <h3 id="5-fifth-position-cinquième-position"><strong>5. Fifth Position (Cinquième Position)</strong></h3> <p>In fifth position, both arms are raised above the head, forming a rounded oval shape. The fingertips are almost touching, and the palms face inward. This is one of the most iconic and elegant positions in ballet, often used in various movements and poses. Fifth position of the arms, combined with other positions of the feet, creates a complete and harmonious line in ballet.</p> <h3 id="tips-for-beginners"><strong>Tips for Beginners:</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Keep Your Shoulders Down:</strong> Always ensure your shoulders are relaxed and down, even when your arms are raised. This prevents tension and helps maintain a long, graceful neck line.</li> <li><strong>Use Your Back Muscles:</strong> Engage your back muscles to support your arms. This will help prevent fatigue and maintain a beautiful line.</li> <li><strong>Practice in Front of a Mirror:</strong> Use a mirror to check your arm positions and alignment. This visual feedback is crucial for self-correction and improvement.</li> <li><strong>Stay Soft and Graceful:</strong> While maintaining the form and structure of each position, remember to keep your arms soft and graceful, avoiding stiffness or rigidity.</li> </ul> <p>By mastering these basic arm positions, you are building a strong foundation that will support you in every step of your ballet journey. Remember, practice and patience are key. With time, these positions will become second nature, allowing you to focus more on expression and artistry in your dancing. Happy dancing!</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="basics"/><category term="technique"/><category term="vocab"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn the fundamental positions of the arms in ballet, a crucial element of classical dance technique. This guide for beginners will help you understand how to position your arms gracefully and effectively, enhancing your overall form and expression.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Order of Barre Exercises in Ballet</title><link href="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/barre/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Order of Barre Exercises in Ballet"/><published>2024-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T21:27:52+00:00</updated><id>https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/barre</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://somersetballet.com/blog/2024/barre/"><![CDATA[<p>For those new to ballet, the barre is often the first stop in every class and serves as the foundation for the rest of the lesson. Each exercise at the barre is carefully sequenced to warm up the body, build strength, and develop technique. Understanding the order of these exercises is key to getting the most out of your ballet training. Let’s take a closer look at the typical progression of barre exercises and why they are structured in this particular order.</p> <h3 id="1-pliés"><strong>1. Pliés</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Pliés, meaning “to bend,” are the cornerstone of ballet technique. This exercise is performed in all five positions of the feet and helps to warm up the legs, knees, ankles, and feet. It also promotes proper posture and alignment.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Pliés start with demi-pliés (half-bends) and then move to grand pliés (deep bends), focusing on maintaining turnout and core engagement. They teach dancers to move fluidly while keeping their upper bodies steady.</p> <h3 id="2-tendus"><strong>2. Tendus</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Tendus, meaning “to stretch,” are performed by sliding the foot along the floor to a pointed position. This exercise helps strengthen the feet and legs while developing the articulation of the foot and the precision of movement.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Tendus are usually performed in all directions: devant (front), à la seconde (side), and derrière (back). The focus is on brushing the floor with the toes and maintaining a strong, stretched leg.</p> <h3 id="3-dégagés"><strong>3. Dégagés</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Dégagés, or “disengages,” are similar to tendus but with the foot lifted slightly off the floor. This exercise builds speed, sharpness, and control, which are essential for more advanced movements like jumps and turns.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Dégagés are executed briskly to help strengthen the dancer’s instep and improve dynamic control. They are often performed in quick succession, emphasizing sharp, precise movements.</p> <h3 id="4-rond-de-jambe"><strong>4. Rond de Jambe</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Rond de jambe, meaning “circle of the leg,” involves tracing a circular pattern with the working leg while keeping the supporting leg steady. This exercise improves hip mobility and teaches coordination and fluidity in movement.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Rond de jambe can be performed à terre (on the ground) or en l’air (in the air). The circular motion helps to loosen the hip joints and develop a range of motion, which is crucial for grand battements and adagio movements.</p> <h3 id="5-frappés"><strong>5. Frappés</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Frappés, meaning “to strike,” are sharp, striking movements of the foot against the floor. This exercise helps develop strength and precision in the feet and lower legs, crucial for jumps and quick footwork.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> The foot starts flexed at the ankle and quickly extends to a fully pointed position. Frappés train the dancer to engage the muscles quickly and prepare for fast, sharp movements.</p> <h3 id="6-fondues"><strong>6. Fondues</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Fondues, meaning “to melt,” are performed by bending both the working and supporting legs simultaneously and then extending them. This exercise emphasizes balance, control, and smooth transitions between movements.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Fondues are often performed slowly to develop strength and stability in the supporting leg while promoting graceful movements in the working leg. They are vital for developing the coordination needed for jumps and turns.</p> <h3 id="7-adagio"><strong>7. Adagio</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Adagio exercises are slow, controlled movements that focus on balance, extension, and fluidity. These exercises develop a dancer’s ability to sustain positions and move gracefully through space.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Adagio typically includes a combination of développés (unfolding the leg), arabesques, and other sustained positions. The slow pace challenges a dancer’s control, balance, and strength.</p> <h3 id="8-grand-battements"><strong>8. Grand Battements</strong></h3> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong> Grand battements, meaning “large beats,” are powerful kicks of the working leg into the air while keeping the supporting leg straight. This exercise helps to increase flexibility, strength, and power in the legs.</p> <p><strong>Details:</strong> Grand battements are performed to the front, side, and back, emphasizing height and control. They prepare the dancer for jumps and other dynamic movements by building strength and flexibility.</p> <h3 id="why-is-the-order-important"><strong>Why is the Order Important?</strong></h3> <p>The order of barre exercises is designed to systematically warm up and prepare the dancer’s body for more complex movements. Each exercise builds upon the skills and muscle groups targeted by the previous one, creating a logical progression that ensures the dancer’s body is fully prepared for center work and across-the-floor exercises. By following this sequence, dancers can develop proper technique, prevent injuries, and achieve a well-rounded ballet education.</p> <h3 id="tips-for-mastering-barre-work"><strong>Tips for Mastering Barre Work:</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Focus on Alignment:</strong> Always keep your body properly aligned and engage your core muscles to maintain stability.</li> <li><strong>Use the Mirror:</strong> Check your positions and movements in the mirror to ensure you’re executing each exercise correctly.</li> <li><strong>Breathe:</strong> Remember to breathe naturally throughout each exercise, as this helps with control and prevents tension.</li> <li><strong>Listen to Corrections:</strong> Pay close attention to your instructor’s corrections and feedback to improve your technique.</li> <li><strong>Practice Consistently:</strong> Regular practice is key to mastering barre exercises and advancing in ballet.</li> </ul> <p>By understanding the order and purpose of each barre exercise, you can approach your ballet training with greater focus and intention. Embrace the barre as a vital part of your ballet journey, and enjoy the process of growing stronger, more flexible, and more skilled with each class!</p> <hr/> <p>This blog post provides a comprehensive overview of the order of barre exercises, explaining their purpose and benefits while offering practical tips to help students improve their technique and confidence in ballet.</p>]]></content><author><name>Giuliana Taylor</name></author><category term="technique"/><category term="vocab"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn the sequence of barre exercises in ballet and their importance in developing technique and strength.]]></summary></entry></feed>