<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="debutballet.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="debutballet.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-12T01:18:42+00:00</updated><id>debutballet.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Début Ballet Academy</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">What to wear for your first class?</title><link href="debutballet.com/blog/2024/uniform/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to wear for your first class?"/><published>2024-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>debutballet.com/blog/2024/uniform</id><content type="html" xml:base="debutballet.com/blog/2024/uniform/"><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to ballet, one thing you’ll do a lot is stare at yourself in the mirror. So, first and foremost, wear whatever makes you feel confident and comfortable. When attending our drop-in classes, feel free to wear comfortable gym attire and go barefoot.</p> <p>If you’re looking to build a classic ballet wardrobe, I recommend checking out <a href="https://www.discountdance.com/dancewear/">Discount Dance</a> for reliable options.</p> <h3 id="leotard">Leotard</h3> <p>The leotard, often called a “bodysuit,” should fit snugly. Personally, I prefer classic designs without lace, as they tend to wear out quickly. Brands like Bloch, Capezio, and So Danca are my go-tos.</p> <p>Here’s one of my favorites: <a href="https://www.sodanca.com/collections/women-dancewear-leotards/products/annie-d379?variant=44510104256674">Classic Black with A Fun Back from So Danca</a></p> <h3 id="tights">Tights</h3> <p>Convertible tights are my preference—they have a hole at the foot which can be rolled up for barefoot dancing or worn with street shoes outside of class. I opt for soft fabric over stiff mesh, as it’s more comfortable, though likely to tear.</p> <p>Here’s what I wear: <a href="https://www.capezio.com/ultra-soft-transition-tight-with-back-seam">Capezio Ultra Soft Transition Tight with Back Seam in Light Pink</a></p> <h3 id="shoes">Shoes</h3> <p>Ballet shoes are typically made from leather or canvas. Many experienced dancers, including myself, prefer canvas split-soled shoes for their flexibility.</p> <p>Here’s my choice: <a href="https://www.capezio.com/hanami-ballet-shoe">Capezio Canvas Ballet Shoe</a></p> <h3 id="pointe-shoes">Pointe Shoes</h3> <p>Pointe shoes are highly individualized and require a professional fitting. Dancers typically begin wearing pointe shoes around age 10 after auditioning and being fitted by a specialist.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="uniform"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some tips on dressing for your first ballet class]]></summary></entry></feed>